Hi, welcome back to the Lam Rim.
And boy, we left this poor lady
whose children had died,
whose parents had died,
whose husbands had died,
who had been buried alive a few times.
And we left her. She finally
came to where the Buddha was.
And something strange happens.
The Buddha stands up far away.
I guess it's in the Garden
of Jetavana, in Shravasti
where he taught the Diamond Cutter.
He looks on her and he says, "Welcome".
It's supposed to be very strange
that the Buddha would stand up
for someone else who walks in
the room and says, "Welcome."
And he says, "Come to me."
Then she's embarrassed to stand up
because she doesn't have any clothes on,
because she was just dug
out of a grave by a wolf/
So here we go.
DE NAS BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS
KUN DGA' BO LA BKA' STZAL PA
Then the Buddha said to
KUN DGA' BO Who is that?
[Student] Ananda. [GMR] Ananda, yay!
BUD MED 'DI LA GOS SKON CIG
means get some clothes on this lady.
Give this lady come clothes.
SKON CIG CES BKA' STZAL PA
BKA' STZAL PA is a very high, high, high
honorific word for he bespoke.
KHO MOS GOS GYON NAS
Then she's telling the story.
KHO MO means me, feminine,
ancient, ancient, ancient.
So this sutra is very old.
KHO MOS GOS GYON NAS
I put the clothes on.
BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYI ZHABS
LA MGO BOS PHYAG 'TSAL TE
I did a prostration to Lord Buddha
and touched my head to his feet.
BDAG LA THUGS BRTZE BAR DGONGS NAS
Please love me. Please show me your love.
BDAG RAB TU 'BYUNG BAR GNOD
Please ordain me.
Please grant me the vows of a nun.
And this GNOD, usually it means
to hurt somebody, G-N-O-D.
But here it's the imperative of NOD PA
which means to grant vows.
So you won't see it.
It's one out of 10,000 something.
She's not asking the Buddha to hurt her.
ZHIG CES GSOL PA
She says, I requested Him.
BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS KUS
DGA' BO LA BKA' STAL TE
Then the Buddha said to Ananda
BUD MED 'DI SKYE RGU'I BDAG MO LA GTAD
Let's turn this woman over to
SKYE RGU'I BDAG MO
SKYE RGU means all the
beings of the universe.
BDAG MO means the lady in charge
of all the beings in the universe.
This is a name for Prajapati,
who was the Buddha's foster mother.
The Buddha's own mother died
about a week after she gave birth to him.
Then he spent his whole childhood
being taken care of by Prajapati.
Then when he became the Buddha,
she became the first nun
of all in this world.
There's a picture of
her here, kind of corny.
I thought, boy, this
picture's probably painted by
some crazy person in France or something.
But it's actually painted in Sri Lanka.
This is a painting of
Prajapati and Lord Buddha.
She was his foster mother.
So Buddha says, "Take this
homeless lady who just crawled
out of a grave and turn
her over to Prajapati."
And she can
RAB TU PHYUNG ZHIG
imperative tense.
She can ordain this woman.
It's also interesting
that the Buddha is asking
a woman to ordain a woman.
Nowadays, I think a guy has
to be there, right Jigme?
[Ven. Jigme] Yes, certain number of guys.
[GMR] Yes, but that's kind of strange.
It seems like in the original
times Buddha's like saying,
all the ladies can take
care of the ladies.
I don't know, probably
changed at some point.
DE NAS SKYE RGU'I BDAG MOS
KHO MO RAB TU PHYUNG NAS
Then Prajapati ordained me.
KHO MO LA BDEN PA BZHI'I CHOS BSTAN
She taught me the four higher truths.
KHO MOS THOS MA THAG TU
Just after I heard
about those four truths:
Everything is suffering,
There's a cause of the suffering.
You can stop the suffering.
There's a path to stop the suffering.
BRTZON 'GRUS SU NAN TAN BYAS PAS
I worked very hard to
practice what she taught me
about the four truths.
DGRA BCOM PA THOB
What's that mean?
I
THOB DGRA BCOM PA
I achieved DGRA BCOM PA
Arhat. I became an arhat. That's so cool.
To be honest, you don't see a lot
of stories of ladies reaching
nirvana in the ancient books
because it was such a
male dominated culture.
But in this story she's the heroine.
DGRA BCOM PA THOB STE
I achieved arhat.
'DAS PA DANG, MA 'ONGS PA DANG,
DA LTAR GYI BYA BA KUN RTOGS PAR GYUR TO
And very importantly,
I gained the power to see
all the events of the past,
the future, and the present.
I could see what was going on,
which is a segue by Lord
Buddha into the next section.
What's the next section going to be then?
They're going to tell the story
of why she got buried
twice and all this stuff.
DGE SLONG MA DE RNAMS KYIS SMRAS PA
Remember that she has
like 500 nuns around her.
She's telling a story.
She's already famous.
What did they ask her to start this story?
How did this story start?
The nuns came to her and
said, "We still feel,
we still feel attracted to guys
and having a nice house.
You know, we became nuns, but frankly,
we're still attracted to guys,
and we're still attracted
to having a nice house and all this stuff.
SNGON LAS CI BGYIS NA
What karma did you do before that
DE LTA BU'I RNAM PAR
SMIN PA MYONG BA STON CIG
that you could get the karmic maturations
that you have described to us?
Since you're an arhat,
you can see all the past history.
So you can tell us why you
went through all this stuff
in the past before you became a nun.
By the way, her motivation
is to encourage them
not to be attached to family life.
DGE SLONG MA AUTPA LAS
KHYED RTAG PAR NYON CIG
You guys, listen up.
KHYED LA BSTAN PAR BYA'O
Now I'll tell you what
happened before all of this,
what was the karma that I
had to go through all that.
ZHES SMRAS SO
SNGON 'DAS PA'I DUS YUN RING PO ZHIG NA
So long, long ago, once upon a time
KHYIM BDAG SHIN TU PHYUG PA ZHIG LA
there was a very wealthy householder.
BU MED PA LAS
He hadn't had a son yet to
carry on his family line.
CHUN MA ZHIG BLANGS
So he took on a junior wife
CHUN MA means a second wife.
Excuse me.
CHUN MA DE LA SHIN TU BYAMS PAS
He had a lot of BYAMS PA to that CHUN MA.
[Student] Love.
Yeah, here BYAMS PA is in
the sense of worldly love.
RING PO MA LON PAR CHUN MA DE
Because of that, before long,
the CHUN MA got a SEMS CAN.
Yes, got pregnant, good.
Remember? She got a sentient being,
meaning she got pregnant.
ZLA BA TSANG NAS
When the time was right.
Second paragraph.
When the time was,
When the required nine months had passed.
KHYE'U ZHIG BTZAS TE
BTZAS means
BTZAS is the Buddhist word for born
because in Buddhism the word
born refers to conception.
So BTZAS means to drop out.
It means come out of the womb.
So we would say born.
KHYO SHUG GNYIS DE LA BYAMS
SHING SDUG PAR 'DZIN TO
And the husband and wife
KHYO SHUG
were very much in love with that boy.
SDUG PAR'DZIN TO
kept him very, he looked
very attractive to them.
This SDUG PA is the SDUG in SDUG BSNGAL,
but it means the opposite.
So this is tricky.
You have to be careful
when you're translating it.
It means they couldn't
keep their eyes off of him.
DE NAS CHEN MAS 'DI SNYAM DU BSAMS SO
Then the older wife,
what... the first wife?
[Student] She got jealous?
[GMR] Well, she got
jealous, right. Of course.
'DI SNYAM DU BSAMS SO
KHO MO NI
She said to herself, I am
RIGS CHE ZHING BTZUN MOD KYI
I am a high cast and I am a spiritual.
I belong to a spiritual cast.
The wanderer cast probably.
BU MED PAS
By the way, this isn't BU MED
This is
BU
MED
Good. BU MED means woman,
which means somebody
without a certain organ,
which is a bad word,
but that's the Tibetan word for woman.
SKYES DMAN which means lower birth.
The two ancient words for a woman.
Probably, wo-man is similar by the way.
And then here it means BU MED PAS
which means I don't have a son.
Therefore, RIGS 'TSOB PA MED DO
RIGS 'TSOB PA
RIGS means the family line.
'TSOB PA means someone to
carry on the family line.
So I don't have a son to
GAL TE KHYE'U 'DI CHER SKYES NA
And then if this boy grows up,
RIGS 'TSO BCING NOR DANG LONGS
SPYOD KYI BDAG POR 'GYUR TE
he will take over the family line,
and he will have lots of
money and possessions.
He will take possession
of all the possessions of our family.
BDAG LA MI STER
And he won't give them to me.
They won't give them to me.
BDAG SDUG PAR 'GYUR RO
Now here's SDUG PA as the opposite.
And I will suffer.
I will want.
SNYAM DU PHRAG DOG SKYES
She got PHRAG DOG
What's that, Tim?
PHRAG DOG
One of the mental afflictions.
She got jealous.
PHRAG DOG
She got very jealous.
BSAD PAR BSAMS
This BSAD PA means to kill.
She thought, she got the
thought, I will kill this child.
And then very terrible story.
BU KHYE'U'I 'TSOG MAR
'TSOG MAR means the top
of the skull of the child.
She stuck a needle in the top
of the skull of the baby.
KHAB means needle.
BTZUGS means she stuck a
needle in the top of the...
RMA YANG MI SNANG BAR BYAS SO
She did it in such a way
that nobody could see that
there was a hole there.
So she shoved a knitting
needle into his head
and took it out slowly,
and made sure nobody could see the place
where she pushed in the needle.
It's terrible, terrible.
I mean, cooking the child.
Now you have to kill your child.
It's very weird.
KHYE'U YANG RING POR MA LON PAR
That boy also before long
TSE 'DAS PA
he passed away, his life passed.
CHUN MA 'KHAMS NAS
And the younger wife, what do you call it?
She fell unconscious.
CHEN MA LA
Then when she recovered, she said,
CHEN MA LA KHYOD KYIS NGA'I BU BSAD DO
She said to the older wife,
I think you killed my child.
ZHES BRGAL TO
This BRGAL means to, sometimes
BRGAL means to cross
the ocean of suffering.
There's a famous verse in
the Bodhisattva Vow Ceremony.
When we say, "I will free those
who have yet to be freed,"
this is the verb used
there to cross the ocean.
But here it means to argue with somebody.
So she BRGAL-ed to the older wife,
"I think you killed my boy."
CHEN MAS BSNYON NAS
means the older wife
denied the accusations.
'DI SKAD CES MNA' BOR
MNA 'BOR means, it's ancient,
these are all ancient, ancient words.
MNA' BO means to take an oath,
to swear on your Bible
or to swear something.
MNA' BOR RO
KHO MOS KHYOD KYI BU BSAD PAR GYUR NA
If it's true that I killed your son,
KHO MOS SKYE BA THAMS CAD
DU KHO MO'I KHYO SBRUL
GDUG PAS BSAD PAR SHOG CIG
Then in all my future lives
may my husbands be bitten
by poisonous snakes and die.
She's like, "If it's true
that I hurt your son,
then in all my future
lives may all my husbands
get bitten by snakes and die."
BU ZHIG YOD NA YANG CHUS KHYER BA
And if I happen to have a son,
may he be carried away by a river
or
SBYANG KYI ZA BAR
or consumed by a wolf.
SHOG CIG means may it happen.
If it's me who killed
your son, then I vow.
This is my vow.
KHO MO'I LUS KYANG GSON POR DUR DU BCUG
And may I be buried
alive in a grave myself.
BU'I SHA ZA BAR SHOG CIG
And may I even eat the
flesh of my own son,
if it's true that I hurt your son.
PHA MA'I KHYIM DU ME SHOR TE
May the home of my parents catch on fire.
THAMS CAD TSIG PAR SHOG
And may everybody that
lives there be burned up.
CIG SMRAS SO
She swore like that.
DE'I TSE NA DE SKAD CES
MNA' BOR BA'I CHEN MA DE NI
"Guess who is the older
wife of those days?"
She says, you know, Utpala.
Blue Lotus is saying,
"Guess who that was?"
KHO MO YIN
What's that mean?
It's me. It was me.
YIN TE
DE DAG THAMS CAD LUS
KYIS MYONG BAR GYUR TO
And then I underwent all of
those sufferings in this body.
DGE SLONG MA DE DAG GIS SMRAS PA
The assembled nuns said to her,
BSOD NAMS CI ZHIG BYAS NA,
SANGS RGYAS MTHONG ZHING
SANGS RGYAS KYIS BSU NAS RAB TU BYING STE
'KHOR BA'I MTHAR PHYIN PAR GYUR
They said, "But now tell
us the karma that you did
to lay eyes on the Buddha,
and to have the Buddha stand up
and greet you and ask you to come to him,
And then for the Buddha to
arrange that you are ordained.
And then to reach
'KHOR BA'I MTHA'
to go to the
Yes, to reach the end
of the cycle of pain.
Can you tell us the good story
of why later in your
life you met the Buddha,
and you got ordained,
and you became an arhat?
What happened there? She said,
AUTPA LAS SMRAS PA
Utpala said,
SNGON W'A RA n'A SI 'DIR
"In a former life, here in Varanasi,"
And Varanasi if you go there,
I mean, it's 5,000 years old.
You can feel it.
The people who live in Varanasi swear
it's a separate universe.
They say it's not part of this world.
And you can,
so many strange things happen in Varanasi.
So anyway,
W'A RA n'A SI 'DIR RI DRANG SRONG LHAGS
there was a place called
the place of the saints.
RANG SANGS RGYAS
There were RANG SANGS RGYASs
NYAN THOSs and MU STEGS CAN.
There were lots of saints living there.
They were self-made
Buddhas, and listeners,
and non-Buddhists who possessed
the 5 kinds of clairvoyance.
Which if you struggled
through Ben Kramer's text,
you know what they are.
DE'I TSE NA RANG SANGS
RGYAS DAG CIG BSOD SNYOMS LA
GRONG DU GSEGS PA DANG
Then there was...
I don't know if the
spelling here is wrong,
but it seems to be a
pair of self-made Buddhas
went to the town, to the city,
to beg for food.
KHYIM BDAG CI CHUNG MA ZHIG GIS MTHONG NAS
The wife of a certain family,
of a certain householder.
RAB TU DGA'
By the way, RAB TU DGA'
is the name of the
first bodhisattva level.
It's called Extreme Joy or something.
She got extreme joy.
By the way, maybe it's meaningful here,
that the same word, I don't know.
BSOD SNYOMS PHUL NAS
She gladly offered a meal to the monks,
MCHOD PA BYAS SO
and made offerings to them.
DE NAS RANG SANGS RGYAS
DE NAM MKHA' LA 'PHAGS TE
Here's the word PHAGS PA.
By the way, these ancient,
ancient sutras are so useful.
So here's the word PHAGS PA
which usually means arya.
Here it means to rise up.
So that self-made Buddha was,
"Mmm. That's a good meal,"
and he rose up in the sky,
LUS LA ME 'BAR
and fire came out his body. Then,
CHU 'BAB
he dropped rain on Varanasi
to make everybody happy.
If you've ever been in
Varanasi in the summer,
it's 44 or 45. People die
walking down the street.
It's so hot. Then,
'GRO BA DANG, NYAL BA
DANG, 'DUG PA'I RDZU 'PHRUL
he showed various miracles
in which he was either walking,
or laying down, or sitting.
These are the traditional
modes of going through the day.
Either you're sitting down,
or you're walking, or laying down.
And he went through,
it means he went through the
whole day showing miracles.
BSTAN NAS KHYIM BDAG GI CHUNG MA DES
That housewife, she said,
KHO MO YANG MA'ONGS PA'I DUS SU
'DI 'DRA BA THOB BAR GYUR CIG
"May I also in the
future become like him."
That's cool.
That's so cool that he's flying in the sky
and he's shooting off fire,
and he can rain on the whole city.
I want to be like him in my future life.
SMON LAM BTAB BO
I made that prayer.
DE'I TSE NA SMON LAM BTAB PA'I
KHYIM BDAG GI CHUNG MA DE NI
The housewife who made the prayer
in those ancient times in Varanasi
KHO MO YIN
What's that mean, you guys?
That was me. That was me.
Therefore, what's she going to say?
What is it?
The translation of
expecting something to come?
What's she going to say next?
That's why I saw the Buddha.
That's why he greeted me.
That's why he got me ordained.
That's why I became an arhat.
Let's check. Anticipatory translation.
DE'I PHYIR DE BZHIN GSHEGS PA
That's why,
PHRAD means that's why I met the Buddha.
And that's why,
SEMS RNAM PAR GROL
that's why my mind was liberated.
And I became a DGRA BCOM PA
I became an arhat.
'DI LTAR DGRA BCOM PA THOB MOD KYI
This a very moving sentence.
She says, "Yes."
MOD means "Yes, okay.
So I did achieve arhat,
but before that I went through a life,
which was like somebody holding a red hot
burning iron tongs at
my feet, to my feet."
It's like someone was holding
red hot iron to my feet
for the whole life before that.
She says, "Yes, I got to arhat.
It was cool, but don't forget before that
my whole life was like
someone was burning me
with a big red, hot piece of iron."
RKANG MTHIL means to the soles of my feet.
We had
MTHIL DU
THUGS DAM MTHIL DU BYUNG
To hold the practice in your MTHIL.
DE'I TSE RIGS CHE ZHING MTHO BA'I
DGE SLONG MA LNGA BRGYA SNYED KYIS
Then these 500 nuns who
were listening to her story
who happened to be of very high cast
before they became nuns,
SMRAS PA THOS NAS
having heard what she taught,
LUS DANG SEMS SKYI G-YA' STE
'DONG BA LA ME MA MUR GYI
PHUNG PO LTAR RTOGS NAS 'DOD
CHAGS KYI SEMS YONGS SU ZAD DE
Their 'DOD CHAGSs ZAD
ZAD Z-A-D.
This means disappearing.
Usually they use it for shoes.
You know, automobile tires,
the rubber wears off,
wears away. Their desires
suddenly disappeared.
Their desire to have a regular
home life just disappeared.
They started to see the
home life like a DONG.
DONG means a barbecue
pit for a cow, "vaca."
ME MA MUR means glowing red embers.
So they started to see the home life
like a fire pit of glowing embers.
Not somewhere you'd want to be.
KHYIM GYI SDUG BSNGAL
LA BTZON RA BAS KYANG
LHAG PAR RTOGS TE
BTZON RA BA means a prison.
This instrumental is the comparative.
And this LHAG PA is
the LHAG in LHAG MTHONG
which means vipashyana,
Which means super, super vision.
So they started to see that the KHYIM
was LHAG than the BTZON RA.
The household life was worse
than being in prison your whole life.
LHAG RTOGS
RTOGS with an s. They suddenly woke up.
They like, oh my god. They understood.
DRI MA KUN ZAD NAS
Suddenly all their
imperfections, 'mala', right,
got vimala.
All their malas got vimala.
They went into TING NGE 'DZIN
and then DGRA BCOM PAR GYUR.
They all became arhats.
The 500 ladies all became arhat
just sitting there with her.
That seems pretty easy to me.
DGE SLONG MA DE DAG GIS TSIG MTHUN PAR
DGE SLONG MA AUTPAL LA BDAG CAG NI
TSIG MTHUN PAR means in one voice.
They said, the 500 new arhatesses
said to the nun,
Blue Lotus, Utpala,
'DOD CHAGS KYIS KUN NAS
BCINGS SHING GLAGS PA LAS
We were...
What's that song? Amazing Grace?
We were chained in our
attachment to the home life,
but you broke the chains and
you taught us to be free.
CHOS BSTAN PAS 'KHOR
BA'I MTHAR PHYIN PAR GYUR
Because you taught us the Dharma,
we have been MTHAR PHYIN.
My Lama's name is MTHAR PHYIN.
We have escaped the suffering of sansara.
DE NAS BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS
If you know sutras well,
you can tell, you could smell
that we're coming to the end,
because then the Buddha
gets up and says something.
DE NAS BCOM LDAN 'DAS KYIS
Then the Buddha stood up.
DGE SLONG MA AUTPA LAS NI
This teaching by the nun, Utpala
LEGS PAR BSTAN LEGS SO LEGS SO
That's awesome.
I can feel like the Dalai Lama
standing up and saying, "That's awesome,
that's a good teaching."
BSTAN TO, GANG CHOS STON PA NI
GCIG GIS GCIG BSTAN TE 'BRAS BU THOB NA
When I see my students
teaching each other,
and somebody gets to
a high spiritual level
because they were sitting
together and teaching each other,
it makes me so happy.
Then I think you are a real
daughter of the Buddha.
Then it makes me feel like
you are a real daughter
of the Buddha.
If I see my daughters
making each other arhats,
it makes dad so happy.
ZHES BSNGAGS SO
This BSNGAGS doesn't mean tantra,
it means he praised them.
He said, "Wow, you guys are so cool."
DE SKAD CES GSUNGS PA
LA 'KHOR MANG PO RJES SU
YI RANG NAS MNGON PAR DGA'O
When he had said that,
everybody was happy.
That's the 25th...
Thhus concludes the 25th chapter
of the Sutra on the Wise and the Foolish
named, The Chapter of the Nun Utpala.
Yay! We're done.
See you next class.
Oh, don't forget why we had this.
Why is this story coming here?
Because Buddha is trying to say,
you can't always see
the relationships that
you had in the past.
Like you could go through your whole life,
unless you become an arhat,
you won't understand why
all the troubles are coming
to you in your life.
And especially you won't
recognize who's been your mom
before.
Cool. Yay!